Roy Gould: Less than a year from now,
روي غولد: بعد أقل من سنة من الآن،
the world is going to celebrate the International Year of Astronomy,
سيحتفل العالم بعام الفلك الدولي
which marks the 400th anniversary
و الذي يوافق الذكرى 400
of Galileo's first glimpse of the night sky through a telescope.
لنظرة غاليليو الأولى إلى السماء عبر تلسكوبه الأول.
In a few months, the world is also going to celebrate
و بعد عدة أشهر، سيحتفل العالم أيضاً
the launch of a new invention from Microsoft Research,
بإطلاق اختراع جديد من نتاج مختبرات شركة مايكروسوفت
which I think is going to have as profound an impact
و الذي سيكون له - باعتقادي - أثر عميق
on the way we view the universe as Galileo did four centuries ago.
على الطريقة التي ننظر بها إلى الكون كما حصل مع غاليلو قبل أربعة قرون.
It's called the WorldWide Telescope,
المشروع يطلق عليه " التلسكوب العالمي "
and I want to thank TED and Microsoft for allowing me to bring it to your attention.
و أود أن أشكر "تيد" و مايكروسوفت لسماحهم لي بأن ألف انتباهكم إلى هذا المشروع
And I want to urge you, when you get a chance,
و أنصحكم ، عندما تتوفر لديكم الفرصة،
to give it a closer look at the TED Lab downstairs.
بأن تأخذوا نظرة عن قرب على المشروع في مختبرات "تيد" في الطابق السفلي
The WorldWide Telescope takes the best images
يأخذ " التلسكوب العالمي " أفضل الصور
from the world's greatest telescopes on Earth and in space,
من أضخم و أفضل التلسكوبات على الأرض و في الفضاء
and has woven them seamlessly
و يقوم بدمجها و بشكل رائع و دون وجود أثر لهذا الدمج في صور موحدة
to produce a holistic view of the universe.
لينتج تصوراً شاملاً للكون.
It's going to change the way we do astronomy,
سيغير هذا الاختراع الطريقة التي ندرس فيها الفضاء
it's going to change the way we teach astronomy
و الطريقة التي ندرس بها علوم الفضاء
and I think most importantly
و الأهم من ذلك باعتقادي
it's going to change the way we see ourselves in the universe.
أنها ستغير نظرتنا إلى أنفسنا في الكون.
If we were having this TED meeting in our grandparents' day,
لو كنا موجودين في هذا الاجتماع في زمن أجدادي
that might not be so big a claim.
لما كان هذا ادعاءً كبيراً.
In 1920, for example, you weren't allowed to drink;
فمثلاً في عام 1920 لم يكن يسمح لنا بشرب الكحوليات
if you were a woman, you weren't allowed to vote;
و لو كنتِ امرأة لم يكن يسمح لك بالتصويت.
and if you looked up at the stars and the Milky Way on a summer night,
و إذا ما نظرت إلى نجوم مجرة درب التبانة في ليلة صيفية
what you saw was thought to be the entire universe.
كنت لتظن بأن ما تنظر إليه هو الكون بأكمله.
In fact, the head of Harvard's observatory back then
في الواقع، رئيس مرصد هارفارد في تلك الفترة
gave a great debate in which he argued
ألقى محاضرة ناقش فيها بأن
that the Milky Way Galaxy was the entire universe.
مجرة درب التبانة هي الكون بأكمله.
Harvard was wrong, big time. (Laughter)
و قد كانت جامعة هارفارد مخطئة، و بشدة.
Of course, we know today that galaxies extend far beyond our own galaxy.
نحن نعلم اليوم بالطبع بأن المجرات تمتد أبعد بكثير من مجرتنا.
We can see all the way out to the edge of the observable universe,
و نستطيع أن نرى إلى حدود الكون المستكشف.
all the way back in time,
و نعود بالزمن إلى الوراء من خلال نظرتنا للكون،
almost to the moment of the Big Bang itself.
إلى لحظة الإنفجار الكبير.
We can see across the entire spectrum of light,
نحن قادرون على النظر إلى كامل الطيف الضوئي،
revealing worlds that had previously been invisible.
ما يكشف لنا عوالم كانت غير مرئية لنا سابقاً.
We see these magnificent star nurseries,
لو نظرنا إلى هذه المجموعات الشمسية،
where nature has somehow arranged for just the right numbers
حيث رتبت الطبيعة النجوم لتكون بالعدد
and just the right sizes of stars to be born for life to arise.
و الحجم المناسبين لتتشكل الحياة حولها.
We see alien worlds, we see alien solar systems --
نحن نرى عوالم غريبة، و نظماً شمسية غريبة
300 now, and still counting --
300 حتى الآن و ما زال العد مستمراً.
and they're not like us.
و هي ليست مثلنا.
We see black holes at the heart of our galaxy,
نرى الثقوب السوداء في قلب مجرتنا،
in the Milky Way, and elsewhere in the universe,
في درب التبانة و في أماكن أخرى من الكون،
where time itself seems to stand still.
حيث يبدو أن الزمن ذاته يتوقف.
But until now, our view of the universe has been disconnected and fragmented,
و لكن حتى الآن، نظرتنا إلى الكون ما زالت مجزأة و ضعيفة،
and I think that many of the marvelous stories that nature has to tell us
و أعتقد بأن العديد من القصص الرائعة التي تريد الطبيعة أن تخبرنا بها
have fallen through the cracks. And that's changing.
قد علقت في فجوات فهمنا للكون. و هذا الأمر يتغير حالياً.
I want to just briefly mention three reasons
أريد فقط أن أذكر باختصار ثلاثة أسباب
why my colleagues and I, in astronomy and in education,
تدفعنا أنا و زملائي في حقل الفلك و التعليم
are so excited about the WorldWide Telescope
إلى التحمس لمشروع " التلسكوب العالمي "،
and why we think it's truly transformative.
و لماذا نعتقد بأنه نقله نوعية.
First, it enables you to experience the universe:
أولاً، يمكنك " التلسكوب العالمي " من اكتشاف الكون.
the WorldWide Telescope, for me, is a kind of magic carpet
فهو بالنسبة إلي أشبه ببساط سحري
that lets you navigate through the universe where you want to go.
يمكنك من الإبحار خلال الكون، حيثما تريد الذهاب.
Second: you can tour the universe with astronomers as your guides.
ثانياً، يمكنك النتقل في الكون بينما يكون الفلكيون أشبه بمرشدين سياحيين لك.
And I'm not talking here about just experts who are telling you what you're seeing,
و لا أتحدث هنا فقط عن خبراء يخبرونك عما تنظر إليه،
but really people who are passionate about the various nooks and crannies of the universe,
بل عن أناس شغوفين بكل زاوية و شق من هذا الكون،
who can share their enthusiasm
عن أناس يستطيعون مشاركتك حماسهم
and can make the universe a welcoming place.
و قادرين على تحويل الكون إلى مكان أكثر ودية و ترحيباً.
And third, you can create your own tours --
و ثالثاً، يمكنك أن تنشئ جولاتك الخاصة:
you can share them with friends, you can create them with friends --
و تستطيع أن تشارك أصدقائك بها، أو تنشئها معهم حتى.
and that's the part that I think I'm most excited about
و هذه هي الناحية التي أعتقد أنني متحمس لها أكثر من غيرها،
because I think that at heart, we are all storytellers.
لأنني أعتقد أننا في داخلنا جميعاً رواة قصص.
And in telling stories,
و برواية هذه القصص،
each of us is going to understand the universe in our own way.
سيفهم كل منا الكون من وجه نظره.
We're going to have a personal universe.
سيكون لدينا كونٌ شخصي.
I think we're going to see a community of storytellers evolve and emerge.
أعتقد بأننا سنشهد مجتمعاً من رواة القصص يتطور و يظهر للعلن.
Before I introduce the person responsible for the WorldWide Telescope,
و قبل أن أقدم الشخص المسؤول عن " التلسكوب العالمي "،
I just want to leave you with this brief thought:
أود أن أدعكم مع هذه الفكرة الموجزة.
when I ask people, "How does the night sky make you feel?"
عندما أسألكم " كيف تشعرون عندما تنظرون إلى السماء ليلاً؟ "
they often say, "Oh, tiny. I feel tiny and insignificant."
غالباً ما يكون الجواب " أشعر بأني بالغ الصغر، و غير ملاحظ إلى حد ما."
Well, our gaze fills the universe.
في الواقع، نظرتنا تملأ الكون.
And thanks to the creators of the WorldWide Telescope,
و بفضل القائمين على مشروع " التلسكوب العالمي "
we can now start to have a dialogue with the universe.
يمكننا الآن أن نبدأ بحوار مع الكون.
I think the WorldWide Telescope will convince you
أعتقد بأن " التلسكوب العالمي " سيقنعكم
that we may be tiny, but we are truly, wonderfully significant.
بأننا قد نكون بالغي الصغر، و لكننا حقاً رائعون، و هامون و جديرون بالملاحظة
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
I can't tell you what a privilege it is
و ياله من امتياز لي
to introduce Curtis Wong from Microsoft. (Applause)
أن أقدم لكم " كورتيس وونغ " من شركة مايكروسوفت.
Curtis Wong: Thank you, Roy.
شكراً لك " روي "
So, what you're seeing here is a wonderful presentation,
ما تنظرون إليه هنا هو عرض رائع
but it's one of the tours.
و لكنه أحد الجولات باستخدام " التلسكوب العالمي ".
And actually this tour is one that was created earlier.
و هي في الواقع جولة تم تحضيرها سابقاً.
And the tours are all totally interactive,
و كل الجولات تفاعلية بالكامل،
so that if I were to go somewhere ...
فماذا لو أردت الذهاب إلى مكان ما
you may be watching a tour and you can pause anywhere along the way,
يمكنك أن توقف الجولة بشكل مؤقت حيثما تشاء،
pull up other information --
و تقوم بعرض معلومات أخرى.
there are lots of Web and information sources
هناك العديد من مصادر المعلومات على الإنترنت و في أماكن أخرى
about places you might want to go --
حول الأماكن التي قد تذهب إليها في جولاتك.
you can zoom in, you can pull back out.
يمكنك تكبير الصورة و تصغيرها
The whole resources are there available for you.
جميع المصادر ستكون متوفرة تحت تصرفك.
So, Microsoft -- this is a project that -- WorldWide Telescope is dedicated to Jim Gray,
إذا مايركوسوفت.. هذا مشروع مهدى إلى " جيم غراي "
who's our colleague, and a lot of his work that he did
وهو زميل لنا، و الكثير من العمل الذي أداه
is really what makes this project possible.
جعل هذا المشروع ممكناً.
It's a labor of love for us and our small team,
إنه عمل بدافع الحب نقوم به مع فريقنا الصغير
and we really hope it will inspire kids to explore and learn about the universe.
و نحن نأمل بحق، أن يلهم هذا المشروع الأطفال ليستكشفوا و يتعلموا عن الكون.
So basically, kids of all ages, like us.
الأطفال من كل الأعمار، مثلنا نحن.
And so WorldWide Telescope will be available this spring.
سيكون "التلسكوب العالمي" جاهزاً للعمل في الربيع
It'll be a free download -- thank you, Craig Mundie --
و يمكن تحمليه بالمجان. شكراً لكم
and it'll be available at the website WorldWideTelescope.org,
يمكنكم تحميله من موقعه على الإنترنت Worldwidetelescope.org
which is something new.
و هو شيء جديد
And so, what you've seen today
إذاً، ما شاهدتموه اليوم
is less than a fraction of one percent of what is in here,
أقل من جزء بالمئة مما يحتويه هذا المشروع
and in the TED Lab, we have a tour
و في مختبر " تيد "، توجد جولة
that was created by a six-year-old named Benjamin
تم إنشاؤها من قبل "بنجامين" ذو السنوات الست
that will knock your socks off. (Laughter)
و ستذهلكم هذه الجولة.
So we'll see you there. Thank you.
سنراكم هناك إذاً، شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
( تصفيق )